We are going to be discussing what DNS is and how DNS works.
DNS server translates fully qualified domain name names into IP addresses and can
invest in translate IP addresses into fully qualified domain name.
Apart from translations DNS is also used to locate the service on a network using DNS
records.
So we are going to learn about DNS record later in this, in this course, so I will show you
some of the DNS records we have, but the services that are located using DNS can be domain
controllers, name servers, mail servers and a bunch of other services.
A common scenario where DNS is being used to locate the service is when on a corporate network
client machines uses the LDAP server to record server records to locate a domain controller.
Let's say we have this domain name kelvglobar.com.
So this is the kelvglobar.com website for the employee to login.
The web address will be www.kelvglobar.com.
So this is the fully qualified domain name of the whole server where the website is running.
In this fully qualified domain name that's fqddn, the dot com is the top level domain.
The center portion which is a kelvglobar is known as the domain name portion.
And the last one which of course is the www is known as the host offering the service.
So it must have seen, it must have seen some where that's fully qualified domain name is
always followed by dots.
But this dot is a root domain and typically this dot is not at all you use on a website.
You can see the examples here at N of it all, you see it dot after the dot com, for
example dot com, then you see another dot, but this dot is not at all used.
But this dot, if you look at a web server, you're going to see this dot there, but on
the inside of by the end user's side, this dot will not be displayed.
So DNS zone is a portion of the DNS namespace that hosts all, hosts a collection of DNS
records as you can see in this image.
For the DNS record, like host record, names of our record, PTR records will all reside
in its zone.
It's a kind of a photo containing all the list files.
So we will see all the different records later in this training.